# **Vivian** Amorim

amorim.vivian@icloud.com | +1 202 790-0650

Brazilian National | Washington DC | I possess the USA Employment Authorization Document

# **SUMMARY**

I hold a Ph.D. in Economics and I have 10 years of experience working with policy-oriented research on labor, education, fiscal, and private sector. I have extensive experience in conducting literature reviews and using data to perform advanced statistical and econometric analyses to foster evidence-based policies. At the Development Impact Evaluation Unit of the World Bank, I have contributed to the design of impact evaluations, data collection, and rigorous assessments of the impact of public policies on socioe-conomic outcomes. I possess a strong quantitative background, the ability to work on large datasets, programming, and data visualization skills. I am accustomed to engaging with academic colleagues and government counterparts and communicating complex concepts to non-technical audiences through reports and workshops.

# **EDUCATION**

PHD IN ECONOMICS UNIVERSITY OF BRASÍLIA (UNB)

Thesis: Essays on public primary education in Brazil

Completed: 2022

MA IN ECONOMICS UNIVERSITY OF SÃO PAULO (IPE-USP)

Admitted among the top 1% of applicants

Ranked as the best school of economics in Brazil

Thesis: The effects of the decentralization of state-managed schools on students' outcomes

Completed: 2013

BA IN ECONOMICS University of São Paulo (FEA-USP)

Graded among the top 5% of graduates

Completed: 2010

# WORK EXPERIENCE

#### WORLD BANK: DEVELOPMENT IMPACT EVALUATION UNIT

**ECONOMICS CONSULTANT** 

Sep 2019 - Current | Washington DC, USA

- Design impact evaluations the theory of change, sample selection, power calculations, survey questionnaires, data collection, data analysis, cleaning, and causal inference.
- Provide proficient coding for harmonization of large and complex datasets, descriptive and econometric analysis, and data visualization. Several of my codes are publicly available in the following links: Kosovo Private Sector, Financial Literacy, School Shutdowns, Child Labor, World Bank Operations.
- Implement robust econometric techniques to assess the impact of public interventions on socioeconomic outcomes and heterogeneous analyses based on sex, income, or intensity of the treatment. Examples of my assessments:
  - A government policy that increased the minimum employment from 14 to 16 years old. I found evidence that there was a 35% decrease in child labor and a 10% increase in the percentage of children only attending school.

- An intervention that promoted financial literacy classes. My results indicate that students' financial proficiency increased significantly and children became more conscious about their savings and consumption behavior.
- A school shutdown policy amid H1N1 pandemic. I found evidence that a 3-week school closure led to a decrease in students' performance equivalent to 6 weeks of learning.
- Generate evidence and provide data visualization to foster evidence-based policies. Examples of my assessments:
  - Estimated that providing loan guarantees to micro and small firms increased in employment (3%), revenue (10%), and productivity (10%), and decreased the probability of closing (5%). Contributions used by the World Bank office, Central and Private Banks to expand the program.
  - Estimated that a civil servant reform would increase the Indonesian central government wage bill by at least 23% in the short run and by 37% in the long run. Contributions used by the Ministry of Finance to negotiate a reform that would have a lower fiscal impact.
- Conduct extensive Literature reviews of public and NGO interventions in several areas such as service delivery, procurement, public financial management, climate change, HR management, and decentralization.
- Disseminate research findings to government counterparts, private sector representatives, and World Bank technical staff and directors.
- Work closely with developing countries such as Brazil, Ethiopia, India, Indonesia, Kosovo, Morocco, Tanzania, Uganda, and Vietnam.
- Write technical reports, and co-authoring of academic papers.
- Support the preparation of Concept Notes and funding proposals.
- Coach junior staff.

#### WORLD BANK: HUMAN DEVELOPMENT UNIT/GOVERNANCE

**ECONOMICS CONSULTANT** 

Jan 2016 - Aug 2019 | Brasília, Brazil

- Cleaned, harmonized, analyzed, and merged large administrative datasets, such as the Education Census, Demographic Census, Household Surveys, and public sector wage bills.
- Performed quantitative and qualitative analyses on labor, poverty, and education. Provided inputs and participated in World Bank dialogues with government counterparts.
- Designed socioeconomic questionnaires to collect data for World Bank interventions, trained enumerators, and showcased pilot questionnaires.
- Developed economic models to simulate the impact of government interventions to foster evidenced-based policies. Examples of my assessments:
  - Estimated that a trade liberalization policy (50% decrease in import tariffs) would lift nearly 6 million people out of poverty in Brazil through consumption and labor market channels. The analysis is included in <a href="Dutz">Dutz</a>, Mark A. 2018. Jobs and Growth: Brazil's Productivity Agenda. International Development in Focus. Washington, DC. World Bank Group.
  - Created a code that uses payroll data to estimate public sector wage bill growth. The program allows the simulation of several austerity measures aimed at helping government officials on policies to guarantee fiscal sustainability. Disseminated the results to policymakers of several states in Brazil. The code has also been run in Honduras, Uruguay, and Indonesia.
  - Estimated the efficiency of public education expenditures across more than five thousand municipalities in Brazil. Found that 1% of the GDP is not allocated efficiently and that students' performance could increase by 40% if local authorities improve the allocation of educational resources. The analysis is included in A Fair Adjustment: efficiency and equity of public spending in Brazil: Volume 1 Overview (English). Washington, D.C.: World Bank Group.

- Represented the World Bank in National Economic Congress and several in-field trips to collect data or present research results.
- Elaborated Terms of Reference for the hiring of staff.

#### INTER-AMERICAN DEVELOPMENT BANK: LABOR MARKETS UNIT

**ECONOMICS CONSULTANT** 

Apr 2014 - Dec 2015 | Brasília, Brazil

- Championed statistical and econometric analysis of labor markets and gender inequality. Provided inputs to IADB technical reports and discussions with researchers and policymakers.
- Partnered with the Brazilian Ministry of Labor to study and design public policies aimed at increasing the efficiency of public employment and decreasing the percentage of informal workers. Worked closely with government officials and secretaries of labor.
- Led the design of informational videos for public employment agencies to sensitize workers on the importance of being better prepared for the labor market.
- Conducted in-field visits to compile best practices and challenges facing federal employment agencies.
- Delivered a training book on best practices to improve job matching between firms and workers and disseminated the findings to municipal and state secretariats of labor.
- Participated in high-level international workshops with research and government counterparts to disseminate the impacts of public policies on labor markets.
- Trained IADB employees at the Brasilia Country Office in econometrics and Stata.

GO ASSOCIADOS ECONOMIST

Jan 2013 – Apr 2014 | São Paulo, Brazil

- Analyzed the economic viability of public-private partnerships in education and infrastructure areas.
- Led the delivery of reports on market concentration impacts of firm mergers.

#### UNIVERSITY OF SÃO PAULO

VBA Programmer

Jun 2011 – Dec 2012 | São Paulo, Brazil

- Developed macros in VBA to automatize the setup of descriptive statistics from a tourism survey conducted in Brazilian airports.
- The code allowed the creation of standardized tables that could be easily reproduced once a new survey wave was available.

#### JP MORGAN CHASE

INTERN OF THE ECONOMIC RESEARCH

DEPARTMENT.

Jan 2009 - Jan 2010 | São Paulo, Brazil

### **TEACHING ASSISTANCE**

**ECONOMETRICS I FOR UNDERGRAD STUDENTS** 

University of São Paulo (FEA-USP)

Jul 2011 - Dec 2011 | São Paulo, Brazil

**ECONOMETRICS II FOR UNDERGRAD STUDENTS** 

University of São Paulo (FEA-USP)

Feb 2012 - Jun 2012 | São Paulo, Brazil

# **AWARDS**

**DEVELOPMENT ECONOMICS VPU AWARD** 

| World Bank

Data and Analytics for Public Employment and Management, 2020

EQUITABLE GROWTH, FINANCE, AND INSTITUTIONS VPU AWARD

WORLD BANK

Comprehensive Modelling to Support Fiscal Sustainability/Brazil, 2019

**HUMAN DEVELOPMENT VPU AWARD** 

| WORLD BANK

A fair adjustment: efficiency and equity of public spending in Brazil, 2018

# **PUBLICATIONS AND WORKING PAPERS**

#### THE SHORT AND LONGER-TERM EFFECTS OF A CHILD LABOR BAN

WITH CAIO PIZA, ANDRÉ PORTELA, AND PATRICK EMERSON

World Bank Economic Review | Code to reproduce the results

# LEARNING WHEN SCHOOLS SHUT DOWN: THE IMPACT OF THE H1N1 OUTBREAK ON PRIMARY EDUCATION STU-DENTS IN BRAZIL

| WITH CAIO PIZA, AND ILDO LAUTHARTE

Preliminary Findings | Code to reproduce the results

# EXPERIMENTAL EVIDENCE OF A FINANCIAL EDUCATION INTERVENTION TARGETING ELEMENTARY AND MIDDLE SCHOOL STUDENTS IN BRAZIL

| WITH CAIO PIZA, AND ISABELA FURTADO.

Policy Research Working Paper 2023 | Code to reproduce the results

# **LANGUAGES**

Portuguese Native Speaker • Fluent English • Advanced Spanish

#### SKILLS

PROGRAMMING TOOLS/PLATFORMS

Proficient: Familiar:

Stata • IAT<sub>F</sub>X • Excel/VBA
R • Python • SQL
Git

# **REFERENCES**

Caio Piza, Senior Economist, World BankD/DIME

□ caiopiza@worldbank.org

Daniel Ortega, Senior Public Sector Specialist, World Bank

Pedro Olinto, Senior Economist, World Bank

polinto@worldbank.org

Christian Lehmann, Professor of Economics, University of Brasília